Eugene Opie Papers ca.1919-1971 Mss.B.Op3
American Philosophical Society
Eugene Opie Papers
Circa 1919-1971
Mss.B.Op3
American Philosophical Society
37.0 Linear feet 37 linear feet
Eugene Opie spent most of his career as a pathologist at the Rockefeller Institute engaged in research on the influenza, tuberculosis, blood diseases, poliomyelitis, and viruses. His work at Washington University, St. Louis, is documented, as are his efforts to alleviate tuberculosis in Jamaica, among Philadelphia schoolchildren, and in New York City. The Opie collection contains correspondence, notebooks, lab notes from his days at Rockefeller, articles, reprints, and photographs. Opie's long interest in China is reflected in material on the American Bureau for Medical Aid to China, the United China Relief, and Chinese medicine in general There is also significant documentation on the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation, the Henry Phipps Institute of the University of Pennsylvania, the Milbank Memorial Fund, and other institutions. There are also reports of approximately 300 clinical autopsies performed at the Base Hospital, Camp Pike, Ark., of soldiers who died in the flu epidemic of 1918. Also there are notes of Opie's course in pathology at the University of Pennsylvania.
Opie, Eugene L., (Eugene Lindsay), 1873-1971
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Scholars of physiology, biochemistry, or biophysics may find the following items of interest:
Du Vigneaud, Vincent, 1901-1978 Correspondence (1 item) 1946 English
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter), 1883-1971 Correspondence (4 folders) 1929-1945 English
Separated Materials note
Photographs have been removed to photographic storage. Biopsy specimens from Opie's Lab, ca.1920s, are stored separately in the subbasement stairwell.
Related Archival Materials note
Johns Hopkins University also contains a collection of papers for Eugene Opie.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Dr. Opie, 1965, and Mrs. Joseph Hughes, 1972.
Scope and Contents note
The Eugene Opie Papers contain correspondence, lab notes, publications, and photographs stemming from Opie's profession life as a research pathologist, educator, and medical school administrator. The collection is strongest for documenting Opie's laboratory work and his work with professional organizations and institutions. There is very little personal correspondence and even the professional correspondence is sparse.
For the forty years beginning shortly after the turn of the century, tuberculosis was one of Opie's major areas of research interest. The collection contains approximately 1.5 linear feet of laboratory notes and reports on tuberculosis, and tuberculosis appears as in folders such as "United China Relief" and "Jamaica."
Materials related to the Rockefeller Institute and Rockefeller University from the late 1930s to 1960s are concerned primarily with administrative and educational matters. The same can be said for the 2 boxes of items on the University of Pennsylvania. Of greater interest are: 1) an 11 page letter from Opie to Theodore Ingalis on Opie's recollections of Phipps Institute, 1923-1932; and 2) Opie's remarks (2 pp.) on eugenics.
Although biographical articles and obituaries of Opie have paid little attention to his work in China, the collection contains 2.5 linear feet of materials on United China Relief and 0.5 linear feet on the American Bureau for Medical Aid for China. While these consist primarily of printed matter such as minutes of meetings, procedure, newsletters, and documents concerned with accounting and administration, there are some items of special interest, including the large manuscript charts providing details on the mode of infection of tuberculosis patients who died.
Other subjects and individuals represented by significant holdings include Jamaica, Cornell University, W. Ekhart, H. Howard, A. Kohlberg, National Tuberculosis Association, P. Putnam, Washington University, and the U.S. Army Autopsies.
Finally, the collection includes approximately 100 typescripts of Opie's articles, plus bibliographic card files for studies related to encephalitis, viruses, and polio.
Biographical/Historical note
The pathologist Eugene Lindsay Opie specialized in the pathologic physiology of viral and bacterial diseases, including tuberculosis, influenza, and poliomyelitis. His career can conveniently be divided into roughly ten year increments. From 1894-1904 he was a graduate student and faculty member at Johns Hopkins; from 1904 to 1910, he was at Rockefeller Institute; from 1910 to 1923 at the medical school of Washington University; from 1923 to 1932 at the Henry Phipps Institute and University of Pennsylvania; and from 1932-1938 at Cornell.
A graduate of the first class of Johns Hopkins' medical school in 1897, Opie developed an interest in medical research while still a student. Under the wing of William Henry Welch, Opie began to investigate sections of pancreatic tissue, discovering that the Islands of Langerhans were absent in diabetics, thus opening the door for an understanding of the origins of the disease. After graduation, he served with the army during the Spanish American War, but returned to Hopkins to take up a faculty appointment as assistant in bacteriology under Welch and pursued his promising work in diabetes. Growing out of his brief military experience, he conducted research into the life cycle of malarial parasites in birds. He married Gertrude Lovat Simpson (d. 1909) in 1902, with whom he had four children. Following her death, he married her sister, Margaret Elizabeth.
Opie's stint at the fledgling Rockefeller Institute (1904-1910) saw his research in tuberculosis begin to gel, and when he moved to the medical school at Washington University (1910-1923), he was actively engaged in studying the pathological physiology of tuberculosis. His career was once again diverted by war, when Opie volunteered for medical duty in France, but as he had during the Spanish American War, Opie made extensive use of his exposure to the extreme disease environment of warfare. In addition to his continuing studies on tuberculosis, Opie worked on largely epidemiological studies of pneumonia and trench foot, and while at Camp Pike, Ark., he performed autopsies on hundreds of soldiers who had died in the flu epidemic of 1918.
In 1923, Opie assumed the directorship of the Henry Phipps Institute in Philadelphia and began teaching at the University of Pennsylvania Medical School, continuing work on the epidemiology of tuberculosis. He is particularly noted for his study of tuberculosis in Jamaica, determining that Jamaicans of African descent were more susceptible to the disease than African Americans. During this period, too, he developed a close working relationship with the Peking Union Medical School in Peking, China, and
Opie left Philadelphia for New York City to assume the chair of pathology at Cornell Medical School and to be come chief pathologist at New York Hospital. He "retired" in 1938, but attached himself to the Rockefeller Institute where he continued working until 1970. His research in immunology and carcinogenesis continued well into his nineties. He received the laurels of his profession, including the Weber-Parkes Prize from the Royal College of Physicians (1945), the Banting Medal from the American Diabetes Association (1946), and the Gold Headed Cane from the Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists (1960).
American Bureau for Medical Aid to China.; Aronson, Joseph D.; Aub, Joseph Charles, 1890-1873; Bachman, George W.; Barker, Lewellys F., (Lewellys Franklin), 1867-1943; Bessey, Otto A.; Brinton, Ward; Cohn, Alfred E., (Alfred Einstein), 1879-1957; Cornell University--Faculty; Cornell, Walter Stewart, 1877-1969; Ekhart, Walter; Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson), 1880-1965; Flahiff, Edward; Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946; Henry Phipps Institute; Howard, Hector Holdbrook, 1873-1960; Isaacs, Joyce; Johns Hopkins University. Medical School--Faculty; Kohlberg, Alfred; Menkin, Valy; Milbank Memorial Fund; National Tuberculosis Association; Putnam, Persis; Robinson, George Canby, 1878-; Rockefeller Foundation. -- International Health Division.; Rockefeller Institute.; Russell, Frederick Fuller, 1870-1960; Sawyer, Wilbur A., (Wilbur Augustus), 1879-1951; Stevens, Helen K.; United China Relief; University of Pennsylvania. Medical School--Faculty; University of Pennsylvania.; Warren, Andrew J.; Washburn, Benjamin Earle, 1885-; Washington University. Medical School--Faculty; Wells, Clifford W.; Articles; Autopsy.; China--Medicine; Epidemiology; Eugenics; Influenza--Epidemiology; Influenza--Research; Jamaica--Medicine; Laboratory notes; Medicine--China; Medicine--United States; Notebooks; Pathology; Photoprints; Poliomyelitis; Tuberculosis--Jamaica; Tuberculosis--New York (N.Y.); Tuberculosis--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care
- Correspondence
  - Abbott, Pat (Box 1)
  - Abel, John Jacob (Box 1)
  - ABMAC - Conference materials. See also: United China Relief, and: American Bureau for Medical Aid to China) (Box 1)
  - Abrev, Manuel (Box 1)
  - Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (Box 1)
  - Adami, J G (Box 1)
  - Adelphi, Jamaica (Box 1)
  - Adoption of standards of the best medical schools of western Europe by those of the U.S. (Box 1)
  - Ahern, J J (Box 1)
  - Alabama State Board of Health, tuberculosis research unit, Lee County. (Box 1)
  - Alabama Tuberculosis study. (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Mrs. James K. (Box 1)
  - Allen, Frederick M (Box 1)
  - Amberson, J Burns (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Tuberculosis Physicians (Box 1)
  - American Association for Cancer Research (Box 1)
  - American Society for Experimental Pathology (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science. (Box 1)
  - American Association of Pathologists (Box 1)
  - American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 1)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China, Inc. (see also: United China Relief, and: ABMC.) (Box 1)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Board of Directors (Box 1)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Bulletin. (Box 1)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Executive Committee. (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid for China Meeting of Medical Committee (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Mecial Personnel (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Minutes of Board of Directors (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Minutes of Executive Committee (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Minutes of sub-committee on civilian medical service. (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Minutes of sub-committee on medical education. (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Reports to executive committee (Box 2)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China. Tentative program for the study of vitamins. (Box 2)
  - American College of Physicians. (Box 2)
  - American Diabetics Association. (Box 2)
  - American Epidemiological Society. (Box 2)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences. (Box 2)
  - American Journal of Clinical Pathology. (Box 2)
  - American Journal of Pathology (Box 2)
  - American Journal of Public Health (Box 2)
  - American Medical Association (Box 2)
  - American Men of Medicine (Box 2)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 2)
  - American Philosophical Society. Committee on Senior Physiologists (Box 2)
  - American Public Health Association. (Box 2)
  - American Society for Experimental Pathology (Box 2)
  - American Standards Association. (Box 2)
  - American Surgical Association (Box 3)
  - Analyses of tuberculosis findings in Smith village, Hannah Town, Jamaica (Box 3)
  - Anderson, R S (Box 3)
  - Angevine, Murray (Box 3)
  - Angrist, Alfred (Box 3)
    General note
    For Biopsy Specimens, ca. 1920's, from Opie's lab see the boxes in the subbasement stairwell (on Fifth St.) From Rockefeller Univ. Med. School, Sept. 1980.
  - Animal Welfare Institute (Box 3)
  - Annual report of the Tuberculosis Programme in Jamaica during 1937 (Box 3)
  - Anti-Tuberculosis League of Jamaica (Box 3)
  - Anti-vivisection (Box 3)
  - Apartment living (New York City) (Box 3)
  - Archibald, Reginald M (Box 3)
  - Arkansas Tuberculosis Association (Box 3)
  - Armand-Delille, P F (Box 3)
  - Army Medical Museum (Box 3)
  - Aronson, Joseph D (Box 3)
  - Arterio-sclerosis (Box 3)
  - Articles: (Box 3)
    - Acromegaly (Box 3)
    - Addison's disease (Box 3)
    - Adrenal Cortex (Box 3)
    - Adrenal - virilism (Box 3)
    - Allergic inflammation (Box 3)
    - Anemia-congenital forms (Box 3)
    - Arrest of mitosis by Colchicine (Box 3)
    - Arsenic (Box 3)
    - Banti's disease and nodular cirrhosis (Box 3)
    - Basophile adenoma of pituitary (Box 3)
    - Blood destruction - anemia (Box 3)
    - Blood formation (Box 3)
    - Blood letting (Box 3)
    - Blood platelets - megakaryocytes (Box 3)
    - Blood vessels at sight of inflammation (Box 3)
    - Blood - volume (Box 3)
    - Calcification (Box 3)
    - Carbon tetrachloride (Box 3)
    - Cellular respiration phosphatase (Box 3)
    - Chloroform (Box 3)
    - Coagulation of blood (Box 3)
    - Comparative Pathology, Inflammation in embryo significance (Box 3)
    - Death (Box 3)
    - Disease accompanying lesions of the posterior lobe of the pituitary (Box 3)
    - Disturbance of iron metabolism (Box 3)
    - Disturbance of vascular system (Box 3)
    - Edema of lungs (Box 4)
    - Embolism (Box 4)
    - Epidemiology of tuberculosis (Box 4)
    - Gigantism with hyperpituitarism (Box 4)
    - Glands - fat of milk (Box 4)
    - Heat - skin burns (Box 4)
    - Hemorrhage (Box 4)
    - Histamine and serotonin (Box 4)
    - Histiophagocytosis (Box 4)
    - Hypertension with tumors of adrenal medulla (Box 4)
    - Hypopituitarism with destructive lesions (Simonds disease) (Box 4)
    - Immunity (Box 4)
    - Inflammation - in relation to special tissues; cornea, cartilage, nervous system, bone, heart, etc. (Box 4)
    - Inflammation - vascular changes, etc. (Box 4)
    - Injury caused by light (Box 4)
    - Intoxification of intestinal obstruction. (Box 4)
    - Irradiation - radioactivity (Box 4)
    - Ischaemia (Box 4)
    - Jaundice (Box 4)
    - Leucocytes (Box 4)
    - Light (Box 4)
    - Melanin (Box 4)
    - Mercuric Chloride (Box 4)
    - Necrosis (Box 4)
    - Necrosis of liver (Box 4)
    - Necrosis of pancreas (Box 4)
    - Necrosis - phosphorus (Box 4)
    - Obstruction of inferior vena cara (Box 4)
    - Ovaries - Pituitary (Box 4)
    - Pancreas (Box 4)
    - Parathyroid (Box 4)
    - Pathological cytology - cytoplasm (Box 4)
    - Pathological cytology - nucleus (Box 4)
    - Peripatetic eduction of a pathologist (Box 4)
    - Pernicious anemia (Box 4)
    - Pituitary (Box 4)
    - Pituitary - cytology (Box 4)
    - Pituitary - diabetes insipidus (Box 4)
    - Plan for the study of the epidemology of tuberculosis in relation to control of the disease (Box 4)
    - Plan for the study of the epidemology of tuberculosis (Box 4)
    - Polymorphonuclear leucocytosis (Box 4)
    - Prolian (Box 4)
    - Protein manuscript (Box 5)
    - Rheumatic fever (Box 5)
    - Schwartzman reaction (Box 5)
    - Sclerosis of the mesenteric arteries of rats and its relation to longevity and inheritance (Box 5)
    - Serious inflammation (Box 5)
    - Shydroxtryptomine (SHT) (Box 5)
    - Spirochetes - course (Box 5)
    - Starvation (Box 5)
    - Statement of the nature and outcome of research work of Dr. Opie (Box 5)
    - Syphilis - congenital (Box 5)
    - Syphilis - experimental (Box 5)
    - Syphilis - frequency (Box 5)
    - Syphilis immunity (Box 5)
    - Syphilis of nervous system (Box 5)
    - Syphilis - pathogenesis (Box 5)
    - Syphilis - S. pallida (Box 5)
    - Thrombosis (Box 5)
    - Thymus (Box 5)
    - Thyroid (Box 5)
    - Toxicity of organic agents (Box 5)
    - Traumatic shock (Box 5)
    - Tuberculosis (Box 5)
    - Uranium (Box 5)
    - Vascular changes of inflammation (Box 5)
    - Vitamin deficiency (Box 5)
    - Vitamins and deficiency (Box 5)
    - Water (Box 5)
    - Xanthomatosis (Box 5)
    - X-rays (Box 5)
  - Asociacion General Antituberculosa de Puerto Rico (Box 5)
  - Association of American Physicians (Box 5)
  - Association of Military Surgeons of the United States (Box 5)
  - Association of tuberculosis clinics of greater New York (Box 5)
  - Association of University Medical Schools (Box 5)
  - Atlee, John L (Box 5)
  - Atwater, R M (Box 5)
  - Aub, Joseph C (Box 5)
  - Auerbach, Murray A (Box 5)
  - Augustine, A. E. (Box 5)
  - Austria - tuberculosis (Box 6)
  - Bachman, George W (Box 6)
  - Bachman, G.W. Report on visit to north-west. (Box 6)
  - Bachman, G.W. Report on condidtion in two group armies at Ichang front (Box 6)
  - Bacteria (Box 6)
  - Baehr, George (Box 6)
  - Baitsell, George A (Box 6)
  - Baker, J N (Box 6)
  - Baldwin, Edward R (Box 6)
  - Balfour, L C (Box 6)
  - Bang, Frederik B (Box 6)
  - Barach, Joseph H (Box 6)
  - Bardeen, Charles Russell (Box 6)
  - Bardeen lecture (Box 6)
  - Barker, Lewellys F (Box 6)
  - Barker, M A (Box 6)
  - Barlow, Nathan (Box 6)
  - Barnes Hospital (Box 6)
  - Barnett, Robert W (Box 6)
  - Barnwell, John (Box 6)
  - Barock, J H (Box 6)
  - Barr, David (Box 6)
  - Barrett, Edward C (Box 6)
  - Barzilai, Gemma (Box 6)
  - Battershill, W D (Box 6)
  - Bauer, John T (Box 6)
  - Bay View Asylum (Box 6)
  - Bayless, William A (Box 6)
  - Bayne-Jones (Box 6)
  - BCG (Calmette) vaccine (Box 6)
  - Beal, George J (Box 6)
  - Bean, William B (Box 6)
  - Beard, Mary: "Nursing needs." (Box 6)
  - Bearn, Alexander G (Box 6)
  - Becker, Walter (Box 6)
  - Beeuwkes, Henry (Box 6)
  - Begg, Charles F (Box 6)
  - Bell, Howard H (Box 6)
  - Bell, Whitfield Jenks, Jr. (Box 6)
  - Belou,Pedro (Box 6)
  - Benditt, Earl P (Box 6)
  - Bensley, R R (Box 6)
  - Berens, Conrad (Box 6)
  - Berger, A L (Box 6)
  - Bergmann, Max (Box 6)
  - Berkson, Joseph (Box 6)
  - Bernard, Léon (Box 6)
  - Bernard, Leon: The onset of tuberculosis in man Abstract (Box 6)
  - Bernecker, Edward (Box 6)
  - Bessey, Otto A (Box 6)
  - Bessey, O. A. Building program for N.Y.C. Public Health Center (Box 6)
  - Bigelow, George H (Box 6)
  - Bishop, E L (Box 6)
  - Bixby, W K (Box 6)
  - Blackfan, Kenneth D (Box 6)
  - Blaisdell, Richard K (Box 6)
  - Blake, Francis G (Box 6)
  - Blakiston Company (Box 6)
  - Blood Bank Army Medical Administration (Box 6)
  - Blood, effects of light upon. Reports (Box 6)
  - Bloom, William (Box 6)
  - Blumer, George (Box 6)
  - Boardman, Mabel T (Box 7)
  - Boisliniere, Louis C (Box 7)
  - Boisliniere, L.C. Realdus Columbus of Cremona (Box 7)
  - Bondurant, Eugene D (Box 7)
  - Boston City Hospital (Box 7)
  - Bowen, Ellen (Box 7)
  - Bowers, John Z (Box 7)
  - Bowman, Henry Adelbert: The Color-top method (Box 7)
  - Boyce, Thomas K (Box 7)
  - Boyd, William (Box 7)
  - Boyle, Patricia A (Box 7)
  - Bragdon, Floyd H (Box 7)
  - Brakeley, George A (Box 7)
  - Branwood, A Whitley (Box 7)
  - Brauer, Ralph W (Box 7)
  - Brink, Frank, Jr. (Box 7)
  - Brinton, Ward (Box 7)
  - British Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 7)
  - British Medical Association (Box 7)
  - Brodie, Donald M (Box 7)
  - Brödel, Max (Box 7)
  - Bronk, Detlev W (Box 7)
  - Brookings (Box 7)
  - Brooks, Barney (Box 7)
  - Brooks, Howard L (Box 7)
  - Broome, John D (Box 7)
  - Broquet, Charles (Box 7)
  - Brown, Thomas Richardson. (Box 7)
  - Brown, J L (Box 7)
  - Brown, Wade. Study of dwarfs, etc. (Box 7)
  - Brown, William Paul (Box 7)
  - Brucellosis (Box 7)
  - Bryner & Company (Box 7)
  - Buck, Pearl S (Box 7)
  - Bunting, C H (Box 7)
  - Burch, G E (Box 7)
  - Burck, Hans Christian (Box 7)
  - Burk, Dean (Box 7)
  - Burlingham, Charles C (Box 7)
  - Burlingham, David(?) (Box 7)
  - Burlingham, Robert (Box 7)
  - Burroughs, Wellcome & Company (Box 7)
  - Burrows, M T (Box 7)
  - Burwell, C Sidney (Box 7)
  - Cabot, Richard C (Box 7)
  - Cadogan, Helen (Box 7)
  - Cahan, Alvin M. Primary carcinoma of the pancreas (Box 7)
  - Cahill, Kevin M (Box 7)
  - Calhoun, J Ellwood (Box 7)
  - California Academy of Medicine (Box 7)
  - Calmette, D A (Box 7)
  - Calvo, Dr. Agglutination of TB treated colloidon pellets (Box 7)
  - Campbell, Charles I (Box 7)
  - Cambell, Editha C (Box 7)
  - Campbell, Glen (Box 7)
  - Canadian National Railways: finances (Box 7)
  - Canat, Eyup (Box 7)
  - Cancer Research (Box 7)
  - Cancer Research Fund: board of directors (Box 7)
  - Cancer Research Fund: U.of Pa. (Box 7)
  - Cancer Research Institute (Box 7)
  - Cannan, R Keith (Box 7)
  - Cannon, Paul R (Box 7)
  - Cannon, Walter B (Box 7)
  - Carcinogins (Box 7)
  - Carey, Cornelius J (Box 7)
  - Carley, Paul S (Box 7)
  - Carnegie Corporation of New York (Box 7)
  - Carr, Francis C., & Co. (Box 7)
  - Carroll, Douglas (Box 7)
  - Carter, Edward C (Box 7)
  - Carter, William S (Box 7)
  - Casals, Dr. TB study. Dissociation experiment in vitro. (Box 7)
  - Cattell, J McKeen (Box 7)
  - Cave, Henry W (Box 7)
  - Cawthon, Kathleen S (Box 7)
  - Cecil, Russell L (Box 7)
  - Central Laboratory (Box 7)
  - Central States Pediatric Society (Box 7)
  - Century Association (Box 7)
  - Chadwick, Henry D (Box 7)
  - Chadwick Clinic results: tuberculosis (Box 7)
  - Chapman, R A (Box 7)
  - Charts - Operations on dogs (Box 7)
  - Chelsea Hotel (Box 7)
  - Chesney, Alan M (Box 7)
  - Children (Box 7)
  - Childs, Jane Coffin, Memorial Fund (Box 7)
  - China (Box 8)
  - China Institute Bulletin (Box 8)
  - China Medical Board of New York, Inc. (Box 8)
  - China - Medicine, etc. (Box 8)
  - Chinese medicine, notes (Box 8)
  - China News Service (Box 8)
  - Chinese Theater - synopsis of plays (Box 8)
  - Christie, Arthur C (Box 9)
  - Chronic infection - Rheumatoid arthritis, etc. (Box 9)
  - Chronic infection studies (Box 9)
  - Cirrhosis of the liver (Box 9)
  - Citizens Preparedness Parade (Box 9)
  - Clark, E R (Box 9)
  - Clark, Paul F (Box 9)
  - Clark, R Lee, Jr. (Box 9)
  - Clarke, Donald C (Box 9)
  - Clarke, Hans T (Box 9)
  - Clarkson, Catherine (Box 9)
  - Clinical notes (Box 9)
  - Clinical Society of Maryland (Box 9)
  - Clough, Harry D (Box 9)
  - Cofman, Victor (Box 9)
  - Cohen, Lord, of Birkenhead (Box 9)
  - Cohn, Alfred E (Box 9)
  - Colby, Helen Opie (Box 9)
  - Colby, Robert L (Box 9)
  - Cole, Dean B (Box 9)
  - Cole, Lewis Gregory (Box 9)
  - Cole, Rufus Ivory (Box 9)
  - Colebrook, Leonard (Box 9)
  - College of Physicians of Philadelphia (Box 9)
  - Colligative properties of solutions (Box 9)
  - Collins, Henry (Box 9)
  - Colorado Foundation for Research in Tuberculosis (Box 9)
  - Columbia University (Box 9)
  - Columbia U. Agreement between Columbia and Public Health Research Institute (Box 9)
  - Committee on Medical Research (Box 9)
  - Commonwealth Fund (Box 9)
  - Communism (Box 9)
  - Congdon, C C (Box 9)
  - Congress of American Physicians and Surgeons (Box 9)
  - Congresso Italiano di Fisiologia, [Tenth] (Box 9)
  - Consultation chest service for private physicians (Box 9)
  - Conway, Herbert (Box 9)
  - Cooper, David (Box 9)
  - Cooper, Eleanor S (Box 9)
  - Cori, Carl F (Box 9)
  - Cornell, Walter S (Box 9)
  - Cornell University (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Medical College (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Council (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Dept. of Pathology. (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Dept. of Pathology - Budget (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Dept. of Pathology - Reports (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Farrand, Livingston (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College - Library (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Pediatrics (Box 10)
  - Cornell Univ. Med. College. Pharmacology (Box 10)
  - Corner, George Washington (Box 10)